Guide to the Muir Family Papers 1915-1956
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Muir Family Papers
1915-1956
Montana State University Library, Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 538, MtBC, us
Muir family
.5 linear feet
The Muir Family Papers include: ranch account books of Joseph Muir's 1915-1927; ranch account books and papers of Nick Muir's 1933-1956; copies of photographs and negatives of the ranch operation near Harlowton, Montana, family members, and sheep.
Historical Note
Nick Muir operated a sheep ranch near Harlowton, Montana from approximately 1930 into the 1960s. Mr. Muir turned the ranch into a family corporation in 1959. He passed away in 1981. His wife, Evelyn Muir in 1996 is the Secretary/Treasurer officer of the Muir Ranch Co. Nick took over the ranch from his father, Joseph Muir. Joseph immigrated from Scotland and worked around the Deer Lodge valley as a ranch hand and later ranch foreman at the Bielenbury Ranch. After marrying Bertha Higgins in 1901, they settled and started the sheep operation near Harlowton, Montana.
The materials in this collection include: ranch account books of Joseph Muir's 1915-1927; ranch account books and papers of Nick Muir's 1933-1956; copies of photographs and negatives of the ranch operation near Harlowton, Montana, family members, and sheep. The photographs are either 3"x5" or 8"x10" and all are black and white. All the negatives are in Box 2, Folder 13.
This collection is open for research.
Financial papers and photographs pertaining to the Muir family ranch were donated to Special Collections by the Muir Ranch Co., Harlowton, Montana, March 27, 1996.
Muir, Joseph, 1863-1937; Muir, Nick
Muir family
Ranches-Montana-Harlowton; Ranching-Montana-Harlowton; Sheep ranches-Montana-Harlowton
Family papers-Montana-Harlowton; Business records-Montana-Harlowton
Ranchers-Montana-Harlowton
Ranching; Montana
- Ledger, 1915-1924 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Ledger, 1915-1927 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Ledger, 1933 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Ledger, 1934 (Box-folder 2/2)
- Ledger, 1935 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Ledger, 1936 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Ledger, 1937 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Ledger, 1938 (Box-folder 2/6)
- Ledger, 1939 (Box-folder 2/7)
- Ledger, 1940 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Ledger, 1941 (Box-folder 2/9)
- Ledger, 1942 (Box-folder 2/10)
- Ledger, 1943 (Box-folder 2/11)
- Account papers, 1956 (Box-folder 2/12)
- Photographs #1-4 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Joseph Muir's home in Glenville, Scotland, #1
  - Joseph M. Muir, Deer Lodge, Montana, #2
  - Mrs. Bertha (Higgins) Muir, #3
  - Bielenbury Ranch workers including Joseph Muir, Deer Lodge valley, [1870s]; #4
- Photographs #5-11 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Joseph Muir, Harlowton, Montana, 1920; #5
  - Sheep at Muir Ranch, 1920; #6
  - Sheep at Muir Ranch, 1920; #7
  - Ranch hands at Muir Ranch, 1920; #8
  - Hauling bales of wool, 1920; #9
  - Ranch hand at Muir Ranch, 1920; #10
  - Baling hay at Muir Ranch, 1945; #11
- Photocopies of newspaper clippings about Mrs. Joseph Muir (Box-folder 2/15)